Ida H. Bond Papers
Ida H. Bond Papers
1896-1931
Bond, Ida H.
1.5 linear ft.
Papers of Ida Bond, resident of Skaneateles, New York; bulk of collection consists of papers written by Bond for presentation to the Portfolio Club, a women's study circle formed in 1875 in Syracuse, New York.
3939418
Biographical History
Ida Hopkins Bond (1851-1943) was the daughter of Barton Marsh Hopkins and Margaret MacDougall of Onondaga County, New York. She was a teacher in the public school system and was for many years the principal of Jackson School, where "She was among the first educators to believe in discipline as a constructive rather than a punitive measure, and her work with difficult cases in the school is still recalled and warmly praised by older members of the school system." Her husband William H. Bond was a hardware merchant in Syracuse. She retired to Skaneateles, where she lived in a home in East Genesee Street that was built by her grandfather, Dr. Judah B. Hopkins, in 1822. At the time of he death in 1943 at age 92 she was the oldest member of the Portfolio Club (a women's study circle formed in 1875 in Syracuse, New York) and of the Plymouth Congregational Church in Syracuse. [Taken from Ida Bond's obituary in the Syracuse Herald-Journal, June 10, 1943.]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Ida H. Bond Papers consists of papers written for the Portfolio Club, a women's study circle formed in 1875 in Syracuse, New York, of which Bond was a long-time member, and a small amount of miscellaneous material.
Portfolio Club papers span nearly thirty years and includes essays by Bond on topics ranging from the history of China to religious practices in New York City. Most, though not all, are annotated with "read at the Portfolio Club" and the date. Some include clippings related to the topic.
Miscellaneous material includes papers written by Bond for other purposes, clippings, a commonplace book filled with poems and saying collected or hand-copied by Bond, a paper by "Florence" on attending the King and Queen's Garden Party in London in 1924, and assorted other items.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged alphabetically by title or topic.
Related Material
See also the
Portfolio Club Records
. Ida Bond was a member of the Portfolio Club for many years.
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Women Authors; Bond, Ida H.; Portfolio Club (Syracuse, N.Y.); Women teachers -- New York (State) -- Syracuse.; Elementary school principals -- New York (State) -- Syracuse.; Women -- New York (State) -- Syracuse.; Women -- Non-formal education.; Women -- Recreation.; Women -- Societies and clubs.; Syracuse (N.Y.) -- History -- Sources.; Syracuse (N.Y.) -- Intellectual life.; Syracuse (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs.; Clippings (information artifacts); Commonplace books.; Correspondence.; Essays.; Minutes (administrative records); Photographs.; Programs (documents)
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Jean Graham, 2009.
Originally, gift of Arthur Bond to the Skaneateles Library, date unknown.
Inventory
- Portfolio Club papers
  - American the Good Samaritan, 23 Feb 1920; YWCA, Red Cross, etc. (Box 1)
  - Ben Franklin and Others, 21 Oct 1929; Benjamin Franklin, Governeur Morris, John Jay (Box 1)
  - Books and Boys, undated (Box 1)
  - Camouflage, Nov 1918 (Box 1)
  - China: Geography and Early History, 1 Oct 1923 (Box 1)
  - Condition of German Women of Earlier Centuries Compared with...Today, 7 Feb 1905 (Box 1)
  - David Lloyd George, 13 Oct 1924 (Box 1)
  - Dixie Land, 3 Oct 1910 (Box 1)
  - Ecumenical Councils, 1914-1915[?] (Box 1)
  - Every Day in India, Feb 1903 (Box 1)
  - From Forest to City, 1907 (Box 1)
  - Fur Companies, undated (Box 1)
  - General Armstrong, Sep 1899; "sketch, can be read in 15 minutes" (Box 1)
  - George Eliot and George Sand in Literature, 5 Feb 1906 (Box 1)
  - Hamilton, undated; "not finished" (Box 1)
  - Harnessing the Nile, 15 Oct 1928 (Box 1)
  - Historical Background of Egypt, 14 Oct 1912 (Box 2)
  - History of William Penn, undated (Box 2)
  - Home Life and Club Life: Their Interdependence, 28 Jan 1901 (Box 2)
  - Japan's Mission Work, Feb 1924 (Box 2)
  - Kings of Israel, 1913-1914 (Box 2)
  - Mormonism, undated (Box 2)
  - Negative [Negation?], undated (Box 2)
  - New York City's Religious Life, 3 Jan 1921 (Box 2)
  - Outdoor Students, 17 Mar 1896; naturalists: Audubon, Burroughs, etc. (Box 2)
  - People of the Long House, Oct 1906; Iroquois (Box 2)
  - Quietness, undated (Box 2)
  - The Red Man and his White Neighbor, 25 Nov 1898 (Box 2)
  - Round the World Tour, 12 Oct 1903 (Box 2)
  - Saint Francis of Assissi, 17 Oct 1927 (Box 2)
  - Social Interpretation of Religion, Oct 1931 (Box 2)
  - Socialism in Europe and Its Significance, 29 Jan 1916 (Box 2)
  - The Socialist and the War, 1914 (Box 2)
  - Socrates: Missionary of the Human Spirit, Jan 1899 (Box 3)
  - Thomas Hardy, 15 Oct 1926 (Box 3)
  - Virgil, Jan 1897 (Box 3)
  - Wit and Humor of the Victorian Age, 1902 (Box 3)
  - Fragments, undated (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous
  - Art prints, undated; about 50 prints of assorted paintings, with descriptions (Box 3)
  - Beautiful book for gifts, poems and sayings collected or copied by Ida Bond; includes numerous clippings laid in (Box 3)
  - English King and Queen's Garden Party..., 1924; handwritten on back, "Florence's paper n the English King's and Queen's Garden Party in London in 1924 given to the Bar Association. Read at the Portfolio Club by Ida Bond, as Mrs. Geo. Bond was in Paris. Mrs. Wiley asked for it. Read in Nov. 1925 (Box 3)
  - Pundita Ramabai and the Child Widows, 16 Jan 1903; "Written for the Women's Guild of Plymouth Church" (Box 3)
  - Tribute to Mrs. H. C. Hooker on the Portfolio Club's 50th Anniversary, by Clara Munnson Smith, 1925 (Box 3)
  - What is Life, undated; unidentified paper, may or may not be Portfolio (Box 3)
  - Miscellanea, list of papers by Ida Bond, no dates; numerous clippings on various topics, possibly related to Portfolio papers; calling card from Mrs. Donald Dey; letter; clipping, "Mrs. Bond going abroad," about Mrs. Bond sailing on the Montreal on June 22, 1922 for a trip to Europe. (Box 3)